Guide to the Cornelia Morse Raymond Papers, 1819-1952 (bulk 1876-1952)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Cornelia Morse Raymond Papers
1819-1952
1876-1952
Raymond, Cornelia M., 1861-1952
2.6 cubic feet (9 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Materials relating to Raymond's life as the daughter of a Vassar College president, a Vassar student, administrator of the College, and unofficial historian. Also included is information about the years she spent as a grade school teacher.
Biographical Note
Cornelia Raymond (1861-1952), the youngest child of nine children of John H. and Cornelia Morse Raymond, first arrived at Vassar when her father assumed the college presidency in the summer of 1864. The pet of both students and faculty, "Nellie" attended the Poughkeepsie Female Academy and was a student in Vassar’s preparatory division. Following President Raymond’s death, the trustees allowed Cornelia and her mother to stay at Vassar until Cornelia graduated in 1883. For the next thirty years Cornelia Raymond worked as a teacher, but returned to Vassar in 1913 to serve as an associate warden. From 1926-1931 she was Director of the Bureau of Publications, and after retiring for two years returned as Publicity Secretary. In both positions Cornelia Raymond managed to serve the interests of the college and to win the respect of the press. She published many articles in college publications; and her book, MEMORIES OF CHILD OF VASSAR, was published on the occasion of Vassar’s seventy-fifth anniversary. After retirement she continued her extensive research in the college’s early records.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, 1892-1951, concerning her work, social activities, responses to questions about Vassar students and faculty, Vassar students participating in a 1934 hunger strike, and other topics primarily relating to Vassar College; manuscripts and notes about her life, including her connections with Vassar and a trip to Alaska in 1939; diaries recording daily activities and personal account books, 1876-1951; congratulatory letters, reviews, and sales records on her book MEMORIES OF A CHILD OF VASSAR, 1940; her personal scrapbook, 1866-1878, and one kept by a relative, Belinda S. Morse, 1819; and photographs.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
16 letters from President Taylor to CMR are with the Taylor Papers:
James Monroe Taylor Papers
Subject Headings
Names:
Morse, Belinda S.; Raymond, John H. (John Howard), 1814-1878
Organizations:
Vassar College--Students; Vassar College--Employees; Vassar College--Faculty
Subjects:
Women--Diaries; Women's colleges--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Hunger strikes; Women college students--Political activity; Women authors, American
Places:
Alaska--Description and travel
Document Types:
Scrapbooks; Photographs; Diaries
VCL Categories
Literature and Writing; Travel; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, February 2007.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the estate of Cornelia M. Raymond.
Container List
- Biographical material (Folder 1.1)
- Letters from Cornelia Morse Raymond, 1915-1951; (24 letters) (Folder 1.2)
- Letters to Cornelia Morse Raymond, ca. 1892-1949; (54 letters) (Folder 1.3)
- Benson Lossing to Cornelia Morse Raymond, 1 Nov 1886; (1 letter and 1 transcript) (Folder 1.4)
- Manuscripts and notes, including notes on trip to Alaska, 1939 (Folder 1.5)
- Bibliography and publications. (Folder 1.6)
- Memories of a Child of Vassar, Poughkeepsie, NY: Vassar College, 1940. Includes letters of congratulation, reviews, and publishing and sales information. (Folder 1.7)
- Photographs. (Folder 1.8)
- Diary, Sep 1876 - Feb 1877 (Box 2)
- Diary, May - Nov 1877 (Box 2)
- Diary, Nov 1877 - May 1878 (Box 2)
- Diary, 1882 (Box 2)
- Diary, Jan-Feb 1885; (typed) (Box 2)
- Diary, 1885 (Box 2)
- Diary, 1886 (Box 2)
- Diary, 1887 (Box 2)
- Diary, 1888 (Box 2)
- Diary, 1889 (Box 2)
- Diary, 1890 (Box 2)
- Diary, 1891 (Box 2)
- Diary, 1892 (Box 2)
- "Line a Day" Diary, 1885-1899 (Box 3)
- Travel Book – Europe, 1906 (Box 3)
- Diary, 1906 (Box 3)
- Diary, 1907 (Box 3)
- Diary, 1908 (Box 3)
- Diary, 1909 (Box 3)
- Diary, 1910 (Box 4)
- Diary, 1911 (Box 4)
- Diary, 1912 (Box 4)
- Diary, 1913 (Box 4)
- Diary, 1914 (Box 4)
- Diary, 1915 (Box 4)
- Diary, 1916 (Box 5)
- Diary, 1917 (Box 5)
- Diary, 1918 (Box 5)
- Diary, 1919 (Box 5)
- Diary, 1920 (Box 5)
- Diary, 1921 (Box 6)
- Diary, 1922 (Box 6)
- Diary, 1923; (typed) (Box 6)
- Diary, 1924; (typed) (Box 6)
- Diary, 1926; (typed) (Box 6)
- Diary, Jan-July 1927; (typed) (Box 6)
- Diary, 1929; (typed) (Box 6)
- Diary, 1932 (Box 6)
- Diary, 1933 (Box 6)
- Diary, Aug 1932 - Nov 1933; (typed) (Box 6)
- Diary, Dec 1933 - Nov 1934; (typed) (Box 6)
- Diary, 1935 (Box 7)
- Diary, 1936 (Box 7)
- Diary (typed), 1937 (Box 7)
- Diary, 1938 (Box 7)
- Diary, 1939 (Box 7)
- Diary, 1940 (Box 7)
- Diary, 1942 (Box 7)
- Diary, 1943 (Box 7)
- Diary, 1944 (Box 8)
- Diary and accounts, Jan-Sep 1948 (Box 7)
- Diary, Sep 1948 - Aug 1949 (Box 8)
- Diary, 1949 (Box 7)
- Diary, Jan-May 1950 (Box 8)
- Diary, June-Dec 1950 (Box 8)
- Diary, 1951 (Box 7)
- Diary and accounts, Jan-June 1952 (Box 9)
- Diary, n.d.; (fragments) (Box 9)
- Account Book, 1923-1929 (Box 9)
- Account Book, 1923-1932 (Box 9)
- Account Book, 1925-1931 (Box 9)
- Notebook: includes diary entries, accts, and various lists (Box 9)
- Notebook: alphabetical directory of political figures, ca. 1945-1952 (Box 9)
- Unidentified fragments, n.d. (Box 9)
- Scrapbook kept by Cornelia Morse Raymond, 1866-1878 (Box 8)
- Scrapbook kept by Cornelia Morse Raymond, 1868-1878 (Box 9)
- Scrapbook kept by Cornelia Morse Raymond, 1879-1883 (Box 10)
- Scrapbook kept by Belinda S. Morse, ca. 1819-1878 (Box 9)